all right we are back it is Jack Murphy
and you're on the Jack Murphy live
podcast the flagship podcast for the
limo order you can find me mostly on
Twitter at Jack Mercer live but
everywhere else Facebook Instagram
YouTube at Jack Murphy live also check
out the liminal order that slim little -
order calm it's our all men's community
where we work on updating our mental
model of the world so we can be a more
productive members of society and today
I have a very special guest somebody who
has had a huge influence on me and on
many others over the last many many
years decades actually but in particular
for me in the last four or five years
the one and only Scott Adams how you
doing today Scott I'm doing great how
are you I'm doing wonderful actually as
I was telling you before hand I'm a
little bit nervous because Scott you've
been such an influential part of my life
actually without even knowing it over
the last number of years when I first
discovered you
I was pretty late to the game I had
certainly known of Dilbert but I didn't
really relate into it too much because
they didn't have the corporate America
experience but my friend our mutual
friend Mike Tsarevich a while back I
want to say it was 2016 one day he did a
book review of your book I think it was
a how to fail and to keep winning that's
not the right exact title but we know it
how to fail and how to fail almost
everything I think right and I'm failing
at that title too so and I noticed Mike
did a review of yours and I wanted to
just sort of start with that because
from my perspective as somebody who's
been operating in the sort of right side
Twitter sphere that was the first time
that I really became aware of your work
outside of Dilbert and I was wondering
if if you could just sort of recap the
way that you and Mike came together
because I think that that did lead to a
number of productive projects and things
and I'm wondering what sort of influence
you saw that that had on on you and your
experience of transforming yourself from
a cartoonist into a political pundit and
somebody that does commentary every day
that's viewed and watched by pretty much
everybody in media well I don't have a
specific memory of
first contact I had with Mike Tsarevitch
but there are a number of people and he
would be chief among them who I've met
in the process of being on Twitter and
talking about you know various political
things so I think if I can recall I
think he was boosting my signal in other
words he was retweeting me and talking
about some of the some of the my tweets
before I had much of a following so he
was one of the the biggest boosters of
my early influence just by giving me a
bigger signal that I could have gotten
on my own and and since then we've you
know I appeared in his movie hoaxed as
one of the interviewers and we've had
lots of conversations including this
morning on you know on Twitter so we
have a pretty much a continuous loose
communication even if we're not talking
directly to each other or we know we're
reading each other's tweets yeah and you
know what was interesting to me about
that connection was that Mike was at the
time writing a lot about mindset and he
continues to do so and if there's a
general theme I can take away from at
least two of the books that I've read of
yours how to fail and then also I just
read looser think a lot of it is about
mindset and it's about controlling your
the way that you think in the way that
you see the world and I was wondering if
you have sensed an increased amount of
attention or interest around this
particular subject matter and if so what
may you attribute that to and if not
tell me why I'm crazy
well I think part of it is that Mike's
book is it reminded me guerrilla mindset
that doing well with the titles today I
mean I think he sold over a hundred
thousand of those and it's it's usually
influential and then my book had a
failed almost everything in still when
big had sort of compatible you know
related stuff I didn't know it at the
time but they they don't overlap so much
as they are compatible I would say and
my book sold you know I'm not going to
give you numbers but it sold a lot II
sold plenty
and there both of these ideas you know
the stuff Mike does and stuff I do
they're the kind of things that people
have to experience by practice in other
words if you if you first hear anything
that we talk about it doesn't maybe not
it's not as powerful
until you observe it what working so
it's the sort of thing you can try and
then if it works you'd do more of it and
so a few years after my book it's
actually starting to crest in popularity
years after I came out because it takes
a while for people to try this stuff and
then report on it and then other people
say what are you talking about you know
in fact exactly like people are gonna
listen to us today they're gonna say
that's the first time I've heard about
those things and so it takes a while for
it to catch on did you do you think that
your book in Mike's book in general sort
of created a market for this because I
was beginning to think that there was
something going on with our society and
our culture that makes this interesting
to us right now maybe identifies a need
that we weren't aware of or there's some
sort of you know mixed-up jumble in our
brain disconnect with reality some sort
of dissonance that is leading people
towards an interest in figuring out how
to control the way we think and control
the way that we frame information so
that it's more beneficial to us rather
than negative so do you think you're
creating the market and the market was
there is there a societal need for this
right now oh it's probably a little both
you know the the market has to be ready
for the message or else it just dies on
arrival so the market was clearly ready
and then on top of that you know I think
Mike and I wrote books that are very
very accessible you know if the average
person can breeze through the making a
lot out of them without a lot of work so
I think that's part of it but the other
thing that's happening on the on the
larger society societal level that may
play into this is I think it is more
obvious than it has ever been that we
live in subjective realities and Trump
you know I don't want to talk a lot
about drunk but he's he's clearly the
person who most exemplifies that you
could see what I call the two movies
playing on one screen that people
living in completely different realities
some people are living in a some kind of
a horror movie
in which everything's gonna blow up any
minute and others of us are living in
the Golden Age it's never been better
and it's not just because it's better
for some people it's worse for others
it's really the same kind of people they
just happen to have different political
views some see it as a tragedy and some
see it as a comedy but they can both
survive and reproduce and work so one of
the things where we're all learning at
the same time and that's what I write
about is that you're not seeing the
world the way other people are you're
just not experiencing the same thing
they are and for all practical purposes
you live in your own subjective world
now that's independent of whether there
is a is a truth below that we don't even
we don't even have to get to that the
only thing we we know for sure is that
we don't have access to it as humans so
that that's an interesting point it's
sort of headed off my next question at
the pass a little bit my last recording
I did was with an artificial
intelligence expert PhD from MIT he's
worked in the field for a number of
years his name is Nick cause Madison
he's gonna be I'll probably release his
a little bit before this one and I asked
him a question about you know computers
and their ability to you know perceived
the world visually and whether or not
that was going to lead us to conclude
that there was an actual concrete
objective reality that you know we can
point to and say yeah that rock is the
rock and that's all the things to it and
look these computers from my very
different angle are seeing it the same
way too would that at the end of the day
to you know sort of definitively show us
that there is an objective reality so
that's my question to you on that
subject and then I guess I think you've
already told me that it doesn't matter
but well it might be true that all
robots have the same subjective reality
I mean I can see that because you'd
program them they'd act they'd act in a
predictable way but if you said okay now
let's take my robot my artificial
intelligence and have it talk to the two
of us who disagree on the reality it
wouldn't work you know even even if you
totally trusted that the robot was
seeing things
realistically you'd still think this
robot was broken if it disagreed it's
like well I see what you're saying but
I'm pretty sure this robots defective
because that's not what I'm seeing so
bee people don't really easily change
their minds about reality itself but but
really I'm talking about interpretations
of reality not not the question of
whether a rock is there or not there we
we generally agree on what the rock is
there or not there right do you how much
do you think our perceptions of an
objective reality and our own subjective
reality then is influenced by our sort
of our DNA and sort of a biological
determinism because in your writing I
definitely get the sense that you I mean
very explicitly say that the information
that we absorb in the language that we
use the language that we're given help
shape our own reality but at the same
time I also struggle with the notion
that you know for example you know can
men and women just switch their genders
and their sexuality is on a whim I don't
I don't know that that's true because I
do believe that there's an element of
our gender expression masculinity that's
tied to our biology and to who we are
chemically you know etc and so to what
extent are those forces working together
in opposition which one is stronger what
do I need to rely on more do I need to
rely on I'm changing the inputs that go
into my head or maximizing the outputs
that come out of my DNA what do you
think about that well in my how to fail
book I talk about humans as being moist
robots in other words the the common way
that people imagine themselves and other
people is that you have thoughts and
then those thoughts translate into your
actions and and certainly that's you
know true ish that that does happen but
the hypnotist view and I'm a trained
hypnotist and when you learn the
hypnosis you you learn that the world is
backwards or upside down if you prefer
and that what really happens is our body
is informing our brain what to think so
you can see that easily if you're let's
say you have kids and your kids are
tired or hung
you know they start fighting and
complaining and yelling and you can't
get him to do anything and then you feed
him a hot dog and then suddenly they
stop complaining they clean up their
room and the first time somebody
explained that to his it was my ex-wife
she said no they're just hungry
and I would look at them and say that's
not just hungry there's something
there's something going on you know
deeply disturbing with these children
and then you feed them and then they
become normal immediately now of course
as an adult you've had that experience a
million times
you know that if depending on your state
of mind the world can look like a horror
or a delight and and once you learn that
if you get your body right if you take
care of your health your your stress
especially you know get to sleep diet
exercise if you get that stuff right
then your brain starts working the way
you think you should have before but if
but if you just start with the brain and
said let me let me think my way out of
these bad thoughts that's a that's a
tough one yeah interesting so if you
took two people who are watching them
the screen and seeing two different
movies and you feed them properly train
them properly exercise them give them
enough sleep make them as comfortable as
possible
is that gonna get them closer to the
same movie or are they still gonna be
seeing two different movies if you can
optimize yourself you're still going to
have those differences yeah you just
look at have those differences the only
difference in that example you gave me
is it's people watching the scary movie
it might be less scared yeah
yeah because if your body is physically
in good shape you can handle stress
better so so that would only be a minor
correlation there is it possible to get
people to watch a different movie
I hear people who say that I have
changed them so I asked after the 2016
election
I did a tweet and which I asked people
if anything I had done had changed their
vote or their opinion about Trump as a
candidate and I think something like if
I recall 1500 people told me that they
changed their entire political view
because of watching me now that's just
how many people
fondant brain so you can usually you
know ten times that at the minimum okay
so I don't know maybe maybe fifty
hundred thousand people changed their
views after watching me but there were
probably people who did not have
super-hardened views so the people who
said you know let's say they were
conservative to begin with and their
first impression of Trump was negative
well they were still conservatives and
he was still promoting conservatives
views so it wasn't that big of a leap to
go from you know being conservative to
embracing Trump it would be really hard
to change somebody from Democrat to
Republican or vice versa ain't changing
demo
hey everybody that's my dog Rosie hey
Rosie my podcast listeners an audience
deaf whoa Rosie and just so happens the
mailman decided to come right that's
we're recording so Rosie thank you honey
I'll probably edit this part out I don't
usually I did anything but maybe this
part so that brings me to another
question is so if people well first of
all Democrats a deplorable is kind of my
whole shtick so if that's that's where
my main focus has been on on myself I
went through a process of abandoning the
Democratic Party I voted for Obama two
times I probably voted for Clinton if I
can remember I never ever voted
Republican knowing my family ever voted
Republican but 2016 was was a time in
which I realized that the Democratic
Party had definitely moved away from me
and that the the the new Republican
Party as embodied by Trump and some of
other elements to it were appealing to
me and so maybe you know maybe I didn't
really change the party has changed I
think that that's one one reasonable
example but if we are destined to watch
two different movies and in doing so
watching those two different movies
leads us to conflict or when I ask you
what what are the consequences of having
a nation that can observe the same thing
and come away with to almost
terrifyingly different conclusions well
first of all it's not new so you have to
if you if you look at the super big
picture or the course of evolution over
the the life of the earth look at all
the animals who
don't understand their reality you know
does a clam understand this reality does
your dog understand its reality really I
mean it doesn't know that the mailman is
delivering mail just just thinks it's an
intruder or something right so
apparently and and I think we can say
this safely because they're just
literally what tens of thousands of
examples and no counter examples we can
see all these creatures who don't
understand their reality they're not
humans but they don't understand that
and yet they could reproduce they they
have everything they need there's
there's nothing lacking if they can
reproduce
that's all evolution demands of you so
what are the odds that humans have
evolved to finally get to the point
where they understand their reality and
you were lucky enough to be here for it
I mean 15 billion years of since the Big
Bang and how lucky that this little you
know hundred year period you just happen
to be born when we figured it all out so
I take it as given that we don't
understand a reality but the the the two
moviepro thing is not that different
from a lot of things we see that work
for example capitalism is you know buyer
and a seller each you're trying to get
it over on the other one it's you know
they're probably nine entertain ten
things fail in capitalism and yet
capitalism works even though it's is
built around primarily failing nine and
ten businesses that's a pretty big
failure rate and if you look at voting
and cap and democracy you know
democratic systems republic etc it's
full of conflict and lying and and and
fake news and it seems like it's just
this big cauldron of violent and evil
and then we wake up in the morning and
we have the strongest economy you know a
super capable military we're safer than
we've ever been and i'd have to say that
the the conflict that we see is largely
a theatrical construct meaning that
because politics is now our new form of
entertainment
and the whole world is watching you see
essentially the exaggerated a hyperbolic
theatrical version of reality and people
you know as a lifestyle they buy into
one version or another but there's
something about the way the system is
designed let's give all credit to the
founders who came up with the
Constitution and yeah we've tweaked it
over time but if somehow handles all of
that conflict all of that stupidity all
of that selfishness all of that fake
news all about lying and produces the
Golden Age and we're at a point where
humans have never looked at a better
situation than we're looking at right
now absolutely so apparently it's not a
problem that needs to be solved because
think them at the the big picture is
things improve basically every year yeah
you know that is a perspective I think
that comes with age when I have these
conversations with my mother no I'm 44
so I'm not young but when I have these
questions with my mom she always takes
those like 10 steps back and she's like
I has just been like that forever and
look where we are now everything's gonna
be just fine don't you worry about it
but then you know you get focused on the
minutia and you and you experience like
for example I went to the Richmond
Second Amendment gun rally on January
20th and while I was there
everyone was super nice there was a
variety of different people diverse
groups of people were there everybody
had their guns out it was like it was
like one one-hundredth of rowdy as any
NFL football game you've ever been to
and it was just like a really lovely
pleasant day and then the news reports
that came out of it were just like look
at all these racists with their guns
what if there were black people there
with guns what would happen then well
guess what there were and they weren't
and they took pictures with them and
everybody was super cool and nice and so
I left that experience which I've had a
number of times my own personal life
being called a Nazi and getting fired
for it even though I was and you know
obviously and each of these times they
still it still managed to cause us
really severe
just I get incensed though a little bit
it really agitated because I feel like
there's something that needs to be
resolved we need to be able to see facts
and and things the same way so that we
can come together we can do happy but
that's what you're you know that's what
I'm saying yeah you're saying no no I
they're all evidence suggests that we
don't need to agree on reality because
we have you know thousands of years of
civilization in which we haven't and we
got this far I mean we made it this far
with all of those flaws and it made no
difference at all now do you think
perhaps these circumstances are
different given the prevalence of social
media and technology
I read her Aires or Harvey sapiens book
and in there he talks about how our
societies coalesced around him shared
imagined orders and then I read a bunch
of technologists and and and media
specialists today that talk about how in
the old days we had a top-down
information distribution system where
Walter Cronkite would tell us all what
to think and feel at night and we were
all unified and we had cohesion today
now because of the liberation of
communication via technology we are not
talking one-to-many we're talking
many-to-many and therefore there's now a
million different imagine orders and now
we don't share in those imagined orders
in the way that we did and therefore
we're now seeing a breakdown in social
cohesion well any weight to that well I
would modify that by saying that we have
two dominant at least political views
you know there's the left and the right
and I've always said that people don't
form political opinions on their own
opinions are assigned to them by the
dominant media now if you ask somebody
they say well it's my opinion but here's
the tell it always matches their
preferred news source always so you know
you could take almost any negative story
about Trump and say okay let's just try
to imagine that this had been reported
as just the facts with no opinion
layered on what would you think about it
and you would find that almost
everything that's alarming and scary and
you know completely inappropriate and
everything else about
whatever whatever complaint they're
bringing today you would find that
almost all of it would just go away if
all you did is describe what he did
instead of having the pundits come on
say well what he was thinking or or
where this will lead us to or what he
really means but didn't say it's all
that stuff they divides us it's not what
he actually does right but I think in
this in this argument people were
talking about how it's not even dominant
news media that are creating new
narratives for us for example our mutual
friend Mike Serna Mitch he's very
successful at creating made media
narratives and they of course spread
into larger institutions and then people
get it from there but there is an
element now I think of a you know we
were sort of like in a unipolar
communication world and now we're in
this multipolar world where everybody's
talking and there's nodes everywhere and
I I just wonder if it's not so easy to
dismiss this notion that failing to
maintain a shared imagined world order
or shared ideas of who we are in our
head because in America at least we're
very much our identity is based on a
shared idea rather than shared genetics
or shared bloodlines that in our
particular case especially since our
nation is one of ideas that if these
ideas are now multiple and diverse and
coming at you from all directions and
able to recruit you into smaller and
smaller teams that they met that may
have a long-term negative effect on
social cohesion that we have not yet
been seen before or or positive because
all this stuff is completely
unpredictable but what I say what I see
is it seems like it used to be a
question of you know you got your
Democrats against your Republicans then
of course you had the media that was a
big player but I think things because of
social media we now see a battle that
seems to be shaping up between two sides
one that has money and the other has
influence now now that you know both
sides have both some money and some
influence etc but people who were
skilled at influence you know they
actually have the tools to influence and
make sort of itches one I'm another
if we have a big enough audience we
become the people who create that shared
imagination you know I I don't mean just
me personally but people were
influential enough to have big audiences
and you know they're good with words and
they understand persuasion so they can
you know package their words just right
it makes things viral I mean if you look
at you know Jack pasaba k-- Mike's or in
a bitch you know or my Twitter you see
that all three of us can generate fairly
viral tweets at will yeah almost every
single day you know all three of us are
hitting at least one that gets a lot of
a lot of retweets usually several so and
and I think that because we have
unlimited reach we are now competitive
with people of money and can buy a can
buy at the New York Times can buy the
Washington Post
can buy this their own channels of
influence I think it's becoming a fair
it's a fair fight now didn't used to be
well that's interesting
frame to put it in yes Jack was so big
late actually even late without Jack and
I are good friends I've known Jack now
for almost half a decade and he is just
one of the finest gentlemen that I have
met period in life and I have nothing
but great things to say about Jack he's
just a good man a family man his wife is
lovely and always loved spending time
with them but he has been on fire lately
his twitter has just been on fire and
you're right he can fire things out at
will and generate massive interest and
spread stories and create narratives and
actually control the legacy media as if
they were on the end of a string and I
wonder to what extent that that reads
that I mean they had the the legacy
media hates you guys and and and and how
much of that is out of jealousy or fear
and and I want to circle back later to
this idea of fear I feel like a lot of
us are motivated we're all motivated
seemingly by fear and so to what extent
is there backlash based on fear or
jealousy and if so and talking to you
about making predictions this is gonna
be fun but so how does that play out
over five or ten years if the
continue on a trajectory slippery slope
just kidding a trajectory like this what
is that what what could happen when
people with money see their influence
slipping they don't like that well
they'll probably try to hire that people
who have influence so I would imagine
that they're gonna try to buy whatever
is working for the other team because
they can but they're gonna have to find
people who were not as independent as
the three people you just mentioned you
know what one of the things that gives
me a superpower if you will and sort of
itch as well is that we're gonna say
things that we think are true even if
you don't like them and we're not gonna
worry too much about what that does to
our career in my case you know my career
earnings when you know down about 30 or
40 percent just by talking about Trump I
can't do speeches anymore that was a
huge part of my revenue I can't do
licensing any more it would be
impossible to do a Dilbert movie if I
tried to do that today because it'd be
there would be too many people would say
hey that guy said something good about
Trump that one time now I've also said
lots of criticisms but but they don't
remember that they'll always see me as a
team so it's expensive and only the only
people can do it are the people who work
for themselves or find some way to
monetize the the danger right right and
if you can't monetize the danger which I
have learned to to some degree given my
experience with the boxing I mean I
don't know - they sent that you know but
I was totally doxxed I had a pen name
totally docks my aunt Eva called me of
Nazi got me fired from my job banned
from coaching Little League basically
stripped away my entire life and
identity my whole resume grad school
career everything up and smoked total
ashes you said your revenue went down
saw mine went to zero went completely
zero and I had this sort of jujitsu it
all into something productive and and I
have been able to do that but not the
people who are gonna be best at that
game aren't gonna aren't gonna sell out
so I wonder to what extent if you're all
or the independent sort of pirate outlaw
in the Bronze Age pervert lingo
continues to gather strength you know
power plays that's basically what
history is all about right big big power
plays and struggle for power I wonder
how it plays out five to ten years the
interesting same well there's like I
said there's a new player in the past
you could be a really influential person
but if you didn't have a platform nobody
cared because you couldn't get your
message him or in the past you might
have a big platform but you didn't know
that the skill of persuasion you didn't
know it was something you could actually
learn and get better at but now you got
both so so it's almost like a warlord
situation where people are bringing you
know a million people with them on
whatever ride they want to take them and
if they're good at giving rides that
that numbers gonna grow yeah fascinating
yeah it warlord is a very interesting
language to use Bronze Age pervert uses
like outlaws and pirates and he uses
imagery of you know like marauding
pirates you know traveling the globe
taking over things and it's all image or
it's not it's not that I yeah I like
mine better because the warlord assumes
that it's one person who's collected an
army yeah and that and that's what
social media is more like you know these
small armies of people who have like
like thoughts
did you read there was an article that
went around called the internet of beefs
did you happen to read that that was
very popular recently no not it was very
very high quality very well done it made
the rounds and it basically described
that we there's like sort of knights
crests and people rally around the
knight and and that it's basically the
Internet is a just a an arena for
conflict and then the people who follow
and the audience's you know they pick up
the banner of the the person that they
support and they sort of follow them all
around the internet supporting them and
going on the ride as as you described it
and what's interesting to me is you
don't need to have a million people
following you in order to have actual
real world influence you know I have
30,000 people which is nothing but more
importantly we have 150 guys in the
liminal order which is our sort of
private community
and it's there where the real influence
is happening the real impacts happen
because those guys are actually changing
their lives and taking steps and
measures that impact themselves and
their families and their communities and
that to me is sort of boom the way that
you build sort of a long-term response
to whatever cultural problems you may
see out there but it is going to be
interesting to see what happens you know
an environment full of warlords is in a
steady state right like that doesn't
last forever
or or is it because like I said in my
earlier examples you know capitalism is
a bunch of robber barons and selfish
people many jerks and you know Crooks
and Liars and yeah just the worst people
in the world but if your system is built
right it produces gold so I don't know
they're having all these these warlords
with different you know idea sets I
don't know that that's bad because good
ideas tend to win now if I'm calling
myself a warlord in this in this context
I don't mean it the bad way because you
know I wake up every day I already made
my money and tried to contribute
something to to society and I work very
hard and making sure that what I do has
a you know a real world you know
individual and collective benefit and as
we talked earlier a lot of my ideas have
bubbled up and become part of society
you know the the idea of talent stacks
the idea of systems being better than
goals those have always existed in some
form but by by capturing them in a
really digestible approachable
accessible form I was able to popularize
them in a way that maybe somebody who
didn't have persuasion and writing
skills could not have so that those
those are two examples of ideas that go
you know they leave me and then they're
they're fighting in the world of ideas
and if they win it's because they
deserved it yeah well those two ideas in
particular really had an influence on me
and it makes metalitz a king in
particular makes a
the sort of innate desire I have to keep
learning things seem more productive
than it may have been before and it also
makes learning things which seem to be
inconsequential or manual or slightly
technical or detailed makes them all
seem much more important too because the
more you continue to add as you know to
the stack the more opportunities you
have like for example for me I feel like
I'm rising out of the din of people on
social media because I actually have a
background that involves economics and
Finance and public policy and I've run
companies and I've developed real estate
and I've written books I've done podcast
you just start to add them all up
together and then you have a unique
perspective that other people don't have
like I can't tell you the number of
times I've had to engage when I worked
in public policy I ran charter schools
so I ran charter schools for ten years
as executive director but I came to it
from real estate perspective an
entrepreneurial background I just cannot
tell you the number of times that I
would be sitting there talking to people
who are running multi-million dollar
organizations that have absolutely no
idea how to run multi core organizations
because all they ever did was work in
education all they ever did was work in
education they just moved over in
education and all of a sudden they're
trying to run these businesses and they
really can't but the talent stack made
it something a little bit more concrete
for me and it's also something that I
know a lot of guys are really grabbing
on to and just continuing to enhance and
and further it's sort of the being an
autodidact and teaching yourself and
expanding your capabilities and
eventually they all just line up and
cross up into something that becomes
unique and and in this world and in this
information environment being unique is
is key and also key is getting
discovered I was having this
conversation the other day and people
ask me all the time how can I get to
where you are or how can I write or how
can I do this and and I tell them like
being discovered is the hardest part
everybody has a platform now but you can
even have great content but getting
discovered is very difficult and I
explained my idea was you have to be
sort of high variance in order to get
discovered what do you think about that
what advice would you give to somebody
who's got talent and a platform
but nobody's listening well I'm gonna
get to give you an opposing viewpoint
here yes
I once asked a table full of high-end
publishers and editors so some of the
best in New York City of the high-end
publishing company and I asked this
question of all the people there
collectively they probably had several
hundreds of years of experience
publishing and I said do there exist
great writers who can't get published
and every one of them said at the same
time
no doesn't exist because and this is
something that that I've discovered you
know anecdotally through my own life
that there is so much hunger for a good
content that if you produce it your odds
of finding a place for or closer to 100%
than zero and I have an implication of
your statement as pretty much well hold
on yeah hold on now it doesn't but it
doesn't mean it happens right away all
right so certainly it takes a little bit
of luck just like everything else but
I'll give you some concrete examples it
was at a co-worker back when I worked in
my cubicle forum at Pacific Bell who
decided to write a book had never read
in the book you know didn't have any
background that was suggested he could
but he saw me write a book and he
thought well if this guy could write a
book how hard is it to write a book so
he just he sets his sight on writing a
book comes up with this great story you
know it doesn't matter what it is gets
published and they asked him to write
another book now of course they edited
all of his writing to you know fix it
and everything but they they liked his
idea and Stephen King has a book called
on writing than they always recommend
paper and what he recommends is that you
start writing for anybody who will you
know take it and that gives you a little
bit of a resume for the you know that
the the person who doesn't pay much but
they're hungry for content and then that
gives you another resume to to ratchet
up very good advice but it but basically
if you can create content that people
want
the the market is actually surprisingly
easy to get published at least now to
your example is here but you're biting
your tongue here because it would
suggest that you know you're thinking
well why don't I have a million
followers already because my content is
great people tell me oh I wasn't
thinking about me I'm fine but but but
you in fact are succeeding so you're so
I would say that the evidence suggests
that your content is excellent because
the evidence yeah you got me on your
show
you got you got thirty thousand people
following you on Twitter and these
things were likely to increase so I feel
that and and by the way cartooning let
me tell you how hard it was to become a
cartoonist I think at least at the time
two thousand people or so would try to
submit comics to become syndicated
cartoonist meaning being in newspapers
and Anna there was two thousand they
might pick five and they would work with
them for a year and maybe only one or
two of them they'll decide to go go
ahead with so you'd say to yourself well
the odds of becoming a cartoonist or
just so bad it's like you know one in
five hundred one in a thousand but then
you talk to the editor who has to pick
cartoonists and you say how many of
those two thousand are actually good and
you find out well a thousand of them
come from the elderly and people in
prison I'm not even making that up maybe
even right and then you know there's
another several hundred of them that
don't have any talent at all and those
can be rejected in moments
so finding anybody who could actually do
the work of being a cartoonist is so
unusual that if you can do it you're
probably going to be a cartoonist and
you're probably going to get paid for it
so if you have talent people are going
to find you if you don't have talent
that's the problem but but but if you do
have talent you're still gonna have to
put yourself out there right you're
gonna have to get noticed right
okay so my discoverability notion is a
little bit still in play but you're
saying that that talent will rise and if
you're consistent and you take what I
think you wrote about you call them
micro steps that you will then be able
to stack up some success and and I think
that I have found that to be true too
you know when I first started out nobody
was listening nobody not anybody you
know I would write a blog post and I'd
be happy if I got 25 views on it I
didn't even know how many of those were
just you know BOTS or crawlers or
whatever and you know now I can be
pretty sure that like thousands of
people are gonna see it and thousands of
people buy the book and come see me
speak and whatever so it's it's very
interesting to see it all happen and I
love to see your description of the
system which you also just referenced
with Stephen King in micro steps and so
that's something that I try to get my
guys to do and I know there's a lot of
people in sort of the self-help Twitter
world that will say and hammer you over
the head is just get started all right
just get started make some mistakes I
think I just read in your book that you
know you do it you make mistakes you get
the most valuable feedback you're gonna
get people will tell you exactly exactly
what's wrong with it the the biggest
difference between a professional writer
who's getting paid for their work and
someone who wants to be a professional
writer is that the professional writer
who does get paid wrote stuff that's the
biggest difference yeah I can't tell you
how many people want to be an author but
they don't write anything if you're not
if you're not writing anything you're
not really moving in that direction
right right yeah and so in a realistic
world today I mean if you want to be a
writer you could start you know
obviously you start your own blog you
could then submit there's a million
websites that are looking for content
probably free at that point at that
point and you're right you just keep
building it over time so but there's one
other element that's right time time is
that other element there how do you how
would you suggest people you know find
the strength or the the stamina to keep
going until that moment that to turn
that was those 10 years into an
overnight success as a where well a
couple of things and I would agree with
Stephen King here I think he recommends
that you keep your day job while your
while
you're doing this other thing so you
don't want to be starving while you're
getting your other thing off the ground
but one of the things I discovered that
it seems to be just a universal truth is
there things which will eventually work
whether it's a product or you're writing
or something
things that will eventually work work
right away and they work in a terrible
forum and I'll give you some examples do
you remember the first cell phones
they're like this big brick and you
dropped your calls and it was expensive
basically everything that could be wrong
with the product was wrong with the
first cell phones but people wanted them
faster than they could be built so that
told you that that was going to be huge
the first computers were just a mess
they were crashing they were slow they
needed floppy disks but everybody wanted
them and you could tell that that wasn't
good to stop so and in Dilbert - when
Dilbert was first published even though
it was a failure for the first several
years because didn't grow an audience
the audience that it did get were just
over the over the moon so it had a very
intense cult following which I said AHA
you don't get that unless there's
something there
so I still had to improve my talent to
take it to the next level I was very bad
when I first started because didn't have
practice being a cartoonist but once I
had done it for a while
I just ratcheted up the quality and
eventually it caught on I mean it takes
a little luck and you have to hang
around a while but people found me yeah
I guess if the moment for me where I
realized that I could actually do make
something of the writing is when people
that didn't know me who weren't my mom
and weren't my girlfriend and weren't my
friends were like oh I read this is
really good oh man somebody who had no
invested interest in their opinion and
it wasn't gonna impact me in any way or
at least their opinion was gonna impact
came out with something positive and
that you know for somebody that's in a
wanting to develop a creative career and
to move forward that those little pieces
little pieces of gold
you really gotta hang on to them it's
like a little Fleck and they just hang
on to it in your palm of your hand and
you get one more like yeah one more
Fleck and you add it up and before you
know it things start taking off and I
think that that's that's sort of where
at where I am right now I've finally
accepted finally because you know I have
issues like a lot of people where you
just can't even believe good things that
are happening like it's so much easier
to believe the bad things that are
happening to you then the good things
but I finally come to the point I think
now where I feel confident that I can
put out good content and people are into
it but in your case you said that it you
Dilbert was a failure for the first
couple of years now that's an
interesting statement because I think a
lot of people would say oh it was a
syndicated cartoon that sounds like
success you're getting paid right you're
getting paid probably every time it gets
published and so a lot of people that
scream success but to you that's said
failure how why how was that failure so
I don't know what the exact number but
something like 405 comics they get
launched don't ever pick up an audience
and then they just slowly go away and
get cancelled so I was in fewer than a
hundred newspapers and they weren't the
big ones the big ones pay more than the
small ones so it wasn't enough to earn a
living I had to keep my day job and it
wasn't growing so the the sales team
they they will sell it when it's new but
if it doesn't sell on its own after that
they they just move on to the next thing
to try to get a hit because it's sort of
it's sort of about hits right it's not
about the average cartoon so once my
cycle had ended and they weren't selling
it actively and it was just the number
of newspapers they were just canceling
and nobody was buying I looked for
something to get attention and I started
putting my email address in the panel of
this trip thousands of people would
write to me every day because they
didn't have and they would say we like
it when Dilbert's in the office
doing work stuff we don't like it when
he's at home and at the time he was
always at home and only rarely in the
office so I said well my background is
not art my background is economics and
Business School and I just heard
thousands of my customers ask for the
same thing all right if you could have a
better indicator of something that's
gonna work it's all of your customers
spontaneously ask for an identical thing
yeah and then so because I'm not an
artist so I don't have the you know they
are you sure are you sure you can still
say that's guy come on well not not me
not the sense of artistic integrity
meaning that I look at my work as I I
guess I
degrade the quality of my own work to
say it's not special it's a product
people like my product or they don't
like my product but it's just a product
yeah it's not like some amazing part of
my body or something so you know I I
just took the business persons approach
and said well if that's what they want
I'll make it a business cartoon and that
immediately allowed people to talk about
it as the business cartoon it became the
the face of downsizing in the 90s it
became the you know the face of the
dot-com thing so just lots of things
happened after that one change so that
brings me to another question too
knowing that you are an expert in
persuasion you know how to use words and
ideas and concepts to your advantage and
you just explained that your art I'm
joking has no integrity has no integrity
but but it's a product responding a kid
responding to a specific market demand
to what extent are all those forces at
play with your Twitter persona and your
periscope persona is that an authentic
expression of your artistic self or are
you meeting a market demand oh I love
that question it's so rare to get it
like a question you've never heard
before when you're when you have my
career I would say that everybody crafts
their personality for the medium
so if I'm writing a blog post I'm a
slightly different person than when I'm
giving a live periscope slightly
different than my interview personality
and slightly different from my periscope
personality
so yes I do craft them but they're all
they're all me I mean none of them are
none of them are I would consider them
inauthentic because they're they're all
just an aspect of me that I either
emphasize or de-emphasize yeah and
that's an interesting part about Twitter
in that people still have this idea that
Twitter is like your personal Canon or
like the ultimate statement of who you
are and your ideas and your beliefs and
your morals and such but and they don't
understand that in order to have some
sort of Twitter momentum or success it
has to be some element of our
performance and it's not inauthentic as
you say but it is it is exaggerated
maybe I don't know some areas are over
emphasized or others and some things are
just meant to be done on a meta Twitter
level that aren't reflective of your
personality or year I'm sorry of like
your true inner beliefs or how you would
deal with your wife if she was sitting
right there or whatever and do use do
you see is that something that people
are ever gonna understand or well be
Bible forever or what your best example
of this multiple personality stuff is
president Trump because he has a Twitter
personality that's different from his
meeting a head of state which is
different from his you know every other
context and what people don't understand
is that when he's on Twitter he goes
into Twitter personality yeah which it
which is far more troll-like you know
it's it's the Wild West and when he when
he enters that frame and becomes the the
Twitter using guy he does it better than
anybody's ever done it yeah it's it's
just that that requires almost you know
a wrestling kind of you know big
personality and then when he's in a
different context he has to meet you
know President Xi or something he just
goes into a different mode and if and
people look at the the tweets and they
say hey the guy who sent that tweet we
don't want him meeting with the world
because look at that craziness and they
still haven't gotten that he can easily
shift from you know he shifts his modes
he just shifts into whatever mode the
situation requires yeah there's a I
think code-switching is another way of
saying that it's a little bit more
specific to linguistics and and just
your your overall communication style
and what's interesting is by for me
working in my schools were 99%
african-american and so in the classes
there you've got the kids speaking sort
of colloquial you know I'm not gonna
Ebonics isn't the right word I don't
even know what they call it black black
English or something but it's like a
colloquial version and so actually the
teacher specifically say listen when you
when you're in school or with your
friends you can speak like this but when
you give a presentation you have to
speak like this and when you go and meet
somebody professionally you have to
speak like this so they're very well
versed in this code-switching idea so I
remember when a OC core test she went
and spoke it like an all black
congregation or something and like
dipped into some colloquial sort of
African American style communication and
she just got completely slammed for that
and to me I'm thinking no that's
perfectly natural you meet and match and
mirror the people that you're talking to
so that you can grin cat ability and
persuasiveness and that's not an enough
inauthentic thing to do so this ties all
together with an another question which
is I have learned and studied all of you
know CLD me and all the persuasion stuff
and Dan Kennedy and copywriting and
everything
am I being inauthentic when I utilize
those techniques is it just me
is there a shadiness to them is there is
there are these weapons that can be used
in the wrong hands is there
nefariousness cand good people use
persuasion morally and ethically well
the first thing I'd say is that we're
all persuading all the time
it's just that we're not necessarily
good at it so when you dress a certain
way you know hold your posture a certain
way use certain words with people
everybody is trying to persuade even if
all they're trying to do is persuade
people that they're cool persuade people
that they're covenant to persuade people
that they're capable so we're persuading
all the time it's just some people are
better at it so I don't know
if there's any kind of moral line we're
simply being good at what everybody's
doing and everybody knows they're doing
it there's no it's not really hidden in
any way I don't see that as being
ethically or morally inappropriate to be
better at the thing that everybody's
doing and accepts as as normal fabric of
the world right right but that makes
sense how often do you ever just put
something out there just to see if the
tools work rather than if the content is
meaningful fairly often yeah so fairly
often I mean it's fun for you right yeah
I mean Twitter is entertainment I mean
as much as information so but the way I
would frame it is to say it's a AP
testing so I mean it's basically just
another word for what you said but I do
put things out and say oh I have a
theory about this one that I think this
one will go back Niq or we're talking
about content well they're inseparable
because your content is part of the
technique okay right but if I put
something out there that's got all kinds
of technique I do watch it to see if I
was right and so for example a typical
viral tweet would be something that's in
the news that day something that people
are really talking about so there's
something about it that makes people
talk and then you you make a clever
connection or a joke sometimes
connecting it to something else they're
talking about like if you could tie you
know impeachment to the State of the
Union in a clever way or anything the
people just recognize that is humor and
they laugh so when I put those kinds out
they're very formulaic
and those are the ones I watched the
most because I'm seeing if the formula
still works interesting and it does and
it still works it's very consistent
Americans yeah and by the way we met you
Jack pasaba k-- yeah I don't know if he
thinks of it this way but he has so much
technique in his tweets it's not a
coincidence that they do well yeah well
I'm saying Jack has been
fire and I watched him go from you know
some sort of five figure number of
followers just transitioning away from
doing nothing but gameofthrones tweets
into becoming a powerhouse in the media
universe and and a White House favorite
and to the you know in drawing the ire
of every political journalist in America
they just can they can't stand that guy
and I think it's better because he
always looks like he's enjoying himself
well he is means he's having the best
time of his life I can imagine he's
living such a good life and I'm proud of
him and really happy to see that was
there was there a formula or something
that did work for you before that has
died is there is there like a hmm if you
know if you come to market with a
product and everybody comes to mark with
the same product that kind of dilutes
the value is there has there been a
technique that that worked that has been
extinguished because it just been
trampled by other people or well there
are some things to get overused the the
one that I'm watching now is and I've
used it a number of times because it's
always funny narrator voice if you do a
tweet and you just say narrator :
whatever you say after narrator is
almost always going to be funny
it's just it's one of those formulas
that almost always works
yeah how I've been I've been trying to
get funnier Scott and it's not really
working for me I've even read books on
how to be funny and it's interesting
because there's there are formulas there
is a technique to it and there are
structures that that work time and time
and time again and one of them is using
the character right as if you present a
character saying something and that
character has one or two characteristics
and they just whatever they say or do
matches with those characteristics
people tend to think that that's really
funny it's just like a program that hits
in people's brains
do you have formal training and humor
writing is that something you've studied
or do you evolved through this through a
and B testing or how did you get to be
to that point you think so in my early
days it was just trial there
but I've developed the formula a
thinking way to sneeze in a minute so
just warning you I'll get Rosie to mark
right then listen
so I've you could Google this to see the
details but I wrote what I call the six
dimensions of humor and the idea is that
you have to use at least two of the six
dimensions or people who will not even
recognize it as humor hmm now I always I
always falter when I'm trying to mention
the six well I'll mention as many as I
can remember for example man so clever
bizarre naughty I'll think of the others
but the point is recognizable is another
one so recognizable is probably the one
you were talking about so recognizable
is if I take Dilbert and I put them in a
situation which other people have been
in they say oh my boss does that to me
all the time I have one dimension but
then I've got to do something clever or
naughty so in other words the punchline
is something you know something heard
him in his butt or there was you know
some vague you know sexual problem
that's not specified because it's a
comic but you know there's something
there or it's a clever almost
engineering solution in the way they
shouldn't have normally worked but does
so if you put together two out of three
you've got something the best the best
cartoonists in the world would start
with two so if you look at carve Calvin
and Hobbes two of the dimensions are
acute and bizarre Calvin and Hobbes had
a cute little kid and a tiger but the
tiger was sometimes a tiger and
sometimes you know stuffed so that was
bizarre plus there was kid who sometimes
talk like an adult that was bizarre
so Watterson would start with two
dimensions before he even wrote a joke
so it's not a coincidence that he had
the most you know probably the best most
people would say comic of all time
and the farside did would had the same
advantage
people at people I did a little tweet a
little tweets that I'm gonna talk to
Scott any questions for him and one of
the questions that came up the most was
have you ever met Watterson and now he
is famous as a recluse and neither of us
have ever made an attempt to meet the
other got it got it
um I have this thing this my kids they
tell me oh I send memes back and forth
we have this whole collection of memes
while we do all day send each other
memes memes memes memes names names how
I understand memes to be an idea but it
seems to me memes
it being changed for the word comic now
they're like one panel comics is there a
relationship there or am I am I missing
that well the memes usually have a
message yeah whereas comics sometimes
are just trying to be funny
I think the meme is usually has a
utility or a function so you're trying
to mock somebody you don't like to
reduce their power so there's always
something you're trying to accomplish
with a meme that a comic is just
entertain interesting are the most
interesting entertaining comics ones
that do have a message in them though
like something or now well it depends
you know in Dilbert comics I oh the
message that's sort of embedded in a lot
of it is that management is silly and
people are irrational and you know we do
things for the wrong reasons we don't
know why were doing it but that's not so
much a social message yeah
if you tried to put tried to be too
preachy in a comic I don't think it
would work so the you bring a subtext is
really important in humor right it's the
message that gets transmitted that's not
over and the messaging do you think
about subtext when you're crafting your
tweets and such or do you just sort of
you have like I imagine you're just so
experienced now that you can just fire
them off the subtext comes out on its
own or do you ever give a system or a
process for that do you ever think
subtext first and then how do i how do i
express that or I've done it in every
direction but the most common direction
that's 95% of the time I would say is
that I start with a situation so
something happens usually it's something
in the real world that could happen to
somebody that's so I get one dimension
so I want to nail the first dimension
this like oh you had that happen to me
and the second dimension could be
anything and if I and if I can add a
third dimension then it's going to be a
home run so it's usually I just built it
up from situation what layer is
automatic and then what layer can I add
to it it's fascinating to me how there
is actual system an actual system to
being funny you you go to watch a
comedian do stand-up and because the
good ones are so good at it it feels
like also when you're reading a book
feels like they're just sitting there
talking to you they're just riffing and
but really it's such an asymmetric
experience right I read your book and
frankly I find your writing to just be
so accessible it's so clear it's it's
fantastic and it's not caught up and
trying to sound fancy or anything which
in and of itself is a fanciness that
most people can't grasp clarity is very
difficult but it's such an asymmetric
experience your book was written in a
draft and ran out on and then a draft
and then a draft another draft it was
edited and revised I've done it a ton
for every paragraph you know there's 50
paragraphs that went before it and but
when you're reading it it's like it just
an instantaneous flow
have you ever reflected upon that and is
there any sort of relevance in sort of
the way I don't really know where I'm
going that so they're just to make this
observation is that the best sort of
writing and communication seems simple
and clear but yet there's like an army
of work that went behind it
yeah very interesting relationship
between creator and consumer very
asymmetric and it's the effort that you
have to put in so one of the reasons
that I added persuasion to my Talas
stack is that as a writer it makes all
of your writing more accessible so
learning to write simple direct
sentences is really about understanding
how the brain works and the cleanest
example that is if I said you have a
choice of these two sentences you're
gonna write about and the first one is
the the ball was hit by the boy
and then the second sentence which means
exactly the same thing the boy the boy
hit the ball yeah now if I say to a non
writer which of those is the right way
they might say well I've heard that a
direct sentence is better but basically
they say the same thing
so I'd say they're about equal yeah and
here's what the persuader knows that
your brain is wired to want to hear this
the person first the boy now I've
imagined a boy now tell me what the boy
is doing he's hitting a ball if you do
it the other way the brain has to work
harder the ball was hit by what what
okay the boy now I have to play it in
Reverse because now I know who started
it and then I can replay it so it's
twice as much work to process the ball
was hit by the boy compared to the boy
at the ball once you learn all of those
simple little wiring truths about a
brain you learn things like we only
remember 10% of what we experience you
know I could go on but and and if you if
you make a long sentence people are just
gonna get bored and tired and they're
gonna wonder why it was so long so I
just don't and it also people don't
process adjectives and adverbs so if you
were gonna write something let's say in
a business context and you wrote it was
very hot yesterday well when you write
it you say to yourself I need to say
very hot because I want them to know
like it's not just 80 degrees it's very
hot well but what the persuader and the
and a good writer knows is that that
person's doctor remember the word very
right there remember it was hot so you
can you can just get rid of all the
words that people aren't going to
remember after they've read it and and
then it becomes clean and simple yeah
and as a reader you can tell when you
hit a passage that isn't hasn't been
well done because your eyes start to
skip over the words a little bit and
then you're like you start think about
something else and you're like oh why
did I just write a paragraph I don't
even I don't even know what I read the
this the best advice I ever got was just
strong nouns strong verbs and if you can
just remember that it sounds so simple
but yet people screw it up all the time
everywhere you go there's so much trash
writing out there that you would think
that nobody had ever heard that simple
principle ever and their whole life why
is it so hard
- right so simply Scott well I think if
you take a writing class in college they
teach you to write complicated yes
there's some sense that it has to be
sort of academic and a certain
vocabulary etc but the the genius of
writing is to write it so everybody
knows what the words mean you know but
you you and I are a professional writers
of a certain age I would say that my
vocabulary if you were to you know
compare to let's say just the average
public probably in the top one percent
just because I do this for a living you
know words or words or what I do and
still I could be reading something on
CNN website not so much CNN but just
some some article and I'll run into a
word I don't know and I think that's not
my fault yeah it's not my fault right
right so somebody's at fault it's not me
right yeah that's it just think the
bigger the vocabulary or have you
realized the less useful it becomes a
time sink because you can't really drop
those words in there one of the things
that your influence on me has one of the
you have influenced me tremendously I
may use some strong strong noun strong
verbs and one of them was systems before
goals and another one all of them sort
of just fit around a mindset and then
the final one was really about thinking
of mental models of the world and and I
can't remember I think you might have
been the one to introduce me to this
just that phrase mental model of the
world mental model of the world meant
amount of the world being broken and I
had sort of taken that to heart that my
perceptive tools this the the ideas I
were I was given the frame of reference
I had none of that seemed to be
producing anything that made any sense
to me anymore like I'm having trouble or
has having trouble making sense of the
world do you think our mental models
that we've had up until now are kind of
broken
do they need updating desire does our
operating software need updating well I
have said it in the last few years that
our whole understanding of reality is
going to change and I think politics
have changed that because we understand
the facts don't matter anymore
yeah we just keep seeing one example
after another where somebody can just
make up facts and it didn't really
change anything and and so I think
that's the biggest understanding is that
we're all living in some kind of a
subjective world now on top of that
you're seeing a big movement toward the
psychedelics so people using mushrooms
and micro dosing LSD and this sort of
thing and I think that that's further
emphasizing that reality is subjective
because if you do mushrooms for example
I'm not recommending it I'm just telling
you what it what it feels like it feels
like you've entered a whole different
world but yet it works you still can
take a drink of water or you could still
you know where the bathroom is
everything works but it's like you're
seeing it for the first time yeah once
you have that experience even once you
realize that the other experience is it
an interpretation and not and not a
infinitely accurate view of the world
and where are you getting evidence that
people are more interested in
psychedelics than they were before I
mean my first thought was like 60s and
and the electric kool-aid acid test that
seemed like a real phenomenon is that
really is this is this just like among
your friends out there in the West Coast
out here in DC I don't hear anybody
talking about that oh yeah in Silicon
Valley
probably everybody beyond a certain
level successes has done some kind of
psychedelics and it probably does about
a regular basis it says it's as common
as as drinking probably and so it might
be different here but what I was talking
about actually was the medical
therapeutic uses because there there are
people who are experiencing breaking you
know alcohol and opioid addictions after
one dose of low dose of like psilocybin
or of LSD or something yeah and several
of those psychedelics not the same
therapy utak value apparently so you're
seeing you know the laws are loosening
up in some places you see more talk of
legalizing more talk of testing more
studies coming out I would say in five
years
now here's my prediction in five years
the the most common treatment for
alcoholism and addiction will be a
psychedelic in five years that's
interesting I have a lot of personal
experience with psychedelics I've
experimented with mushrooms and MDMA but
especially back in the 90s for sure and
I will say without any doubt my
experience with MDMA or ecstasy or Molly
or whatever the kids are calling it
these days completely transform my ideas
of reality and enhance my senses of
empathy made me feel connected to other
people in a way that I hadn't ordinarily
and interestingly enough it was those
experiences that really solidified me to
think I was on the left to think that I
was liberal and loved everybody and and
became much more accepting of everyone
and have just a variety of experiences
you know of course we're hanging out
with people from the fringes at that
time of society so it was sort of like a
twilight space of culture you know like
the right before sunset and that weird
glow and it was just a I would highly
recommend it but I don't really
recommend it I can't recommend you do
drugs on this podcast but it was hugely
influential on me and I know it was
influential on you and even in your your
persuasion book list where I think there
were references to people that like
maples Timothy Leary on there I don't
know it's just sort of the experience of
opening your mind using drugs to
alternate realities would you prescribe
no you're not going to prescribe do you
think that those types of experiences
are essential to understanding just sort
of the environment that we live in and
this the the experience that we're
having in this universe well almost
everybody who goes to these experiences
says the same thing which is okay it's
I'm forever different now that that's
not like having a drink yeah yeah you
can get pretty drunk and you're the same
person after you're sober but you loosen
again you do a hallucinogen once and
your whole worldview will change and it
won't go back so that's the big
difference yeah that's interesting I
doubt that our nation or maybe we'll
ever have widely accepted this No
everybody needs to take a trip into its
corner to come yeah let me just for the
purpose of safety yeah there's not
there's nothing I've mentioned that I
think is a good idea without medical
supervision and see if you have some
underlying mental issues or you're on
other kinds of drugs it's some dangerous
stuff so don't do this lightly but I
think the medical world will embrace
this within five years you know it we've
done a little bit over an hour here and
I have a few more questions and and one
of them is I appreciate you coming on
the podcast my question to you is why
why did you and not me in particular but
why do you why are you so accessible to
people who are looking to interview you
alternate media like this what what is
it about how does that fit into your
game plan Scott well of course I always
have a book out that I'm promoting so
the latest is loser think and I decided
that after seeing lots of regular media
hits and then I'll watch you know what
happens to the book sales and then you
go on James Alta sure I got a plan you
know it explodes yeah and yeah he's just
one example but podcasts are the the new
most legitimate way to for an author to
to get known because there's two minute
hits on CNN or Fox News don't tell you
anything they just put your face out
there yeah interesting well I can
appreciate that but it's also just a for
me personally I've been doing other
people's podcast now because I find a I
just need practice talking and I just
like enjoy actually talking to people I
always leave these conversations feeling
more energetic than beforehand I got to
say Scott I was a little nervous for
this one that's not good persuasion but
I was a little nervous and I used one of
your tricks to calm me down a little bit
but I was very excited at this
opportunity to sit down with you because
truly I for my world changed
dramatically 2015 onwards after I got
onto Twitter I mean I put my friend Mike
and I have been friends since five years
before he even got on Twitter like I was
I was in
like sweating like I've known him way
before any of this stuff happens so I
followed him onto Twitter and I didn't
know what the hell I was getting into or
what was gonna happen to my life but
like my life is completely totally 100%
different than it was then completely
new professional career completely new
social life completely new perspective
on the world and you know you were you
were definitely a part of that and your
books have been a part of that and I
just want to say thank you first of all
for putting some great ideas into my
head and for sort of leading the way in
this new medium and being like a real
sort of torch bearer for this new system
of communication which is still even
though feels like it's been around for a
little bit it's still like totally in
its infancy this this new way of us
communicating is just brand new and in a
you know historical sense it's all just
began immediately right now we don't
even know where it's gonna go or what
it's going to do and you're effectively
a pioneer so it's a it's been fun to
watch and I really appreciate that on
this journey for you what has been the
highlight of becoming a social media
star and and what has become what was
become the what was the law and if you
knew then what you know now would you
have still done it the answer is yes I
would still do it I would say the the
low points or any day that there's some
you know scurrilous rumor about me and
the the paid trolls come in by the
thousands and make my life miserable for
a while and mostly it's just
inconvenience I don't like taking all
the time to block them all so it's just
taking my time but for some reason most
of the professional trolls let have left
me alone for the last month and I don't
know why but they all just disappeared
which also tells you they're organized
there are organized if anybody's
listening to this who doesn't know both
both sides left and right have organized
troll armies you don't always know who's
controlling them but you know when they
arrive because they all they all say the
same thing and they arrive at the same
time so those are all bad days the best
day by far and I think
Twitter had a lot to do with it was
getting invited to the Oval Office to
chat with the president just because he
was it was working his his supporters
basically and and that was by far I
think will be my coolest life experience
yeah just just going there being in the
Oval Office talking to the President of
the United States about whatever we
wanted to talk about for about half an
hour I'm never gonna be able to match
that as an experience yeah Wow a half an
hour man that's pretty good it wasn't
just a handshake in the line or whatever
that's awesome that's awesome well
congratulations on that congratulations
on your success the latest book loser
think what is and what were the last
couple was when Begley was one before
that right and what that was how to fail
at almost everything had a failed almost
everything and still win big and still
win big all of which have a certain
self-help element to them and I wonder
Scott the inside of you there there's
somebody that wants to help people isn't
that right yeah primarily I Oh effing
describe the perfect life arc as being
born as a baby and you're perfectly
selfish because you can't do anything
for yourself anyway then we get a little
older and maybe can help out around the
house by the time you're an adult and a
parent you're probably doing more for
your kids and your job and your spouse
and you are for yourself and by the time
you die if you've done everything right
your last moment you know as the life is
extinguished from your body you
literally give up everything you've
accumulated you you're right you just
give it all up so your last moment of
life and as you transition is the
ultimate unselfish act you give away
everything and but and ideally you've
you've left good ideas and influence and
and an advice so I thought well I'm an
author why don't I put this in a book
you know well I will boost my signal and
I thought I had things to say but you
don't really know until the books out
there and people respond to it and after
I wrote I had a fail I mean it was just
wildly successful and people still talk
to me everyday people say I lost 80
pounds I got off of drugs I got a job I
got a promotion based on stuff in the
book
so that that kind of encourages you to
do more because you know monetarily
doesn't make that much difference to me
these days but having that influence and
seeing people's lives improve I mean
that's a really big payback I mean
that's just deeply deeply satisfying it
really is and you should be commended
for that and I wish the people that gave
you so much hassle online would realize
that deep inside not even deep inside
very much on the surface is somebody
that is really just trying to help
people out and is trying to spread good
information useful things that's gonna
lead to direct improvements in people's
lives and I can say I'm one of those
people and I can say that some of those
concepts
I have also now leveraged up into
influencing other people myself and so
there's an exponential effect to it so
thank you for that thank you for coming
on the show I really appreciate it
thanks for being a good sport and
answering some of the some of the
questions honestly I really appreciate
that to Scott and you know just keep on
doing what you're doing and I'll keep
watching and thank you very much thanks
jack thanks for having me and good luck
with everything all right thanks a lot I
appreciate it
[Music]
you